当你俯瞰地球表面
When you look down the Earth's surface
让人无法不为自然界的力量
it's impossible not to be impressed
与其纯粹的宏伟壮丽
by the sheer grandeur,splendour and power
而叹为观止
of the natural world.
我们呈现了众多这样的奇迹
It's been ten years since we explored these wonders
在《地球脉动》这一电视节目中
in the first series of Planet Earth.
时至今日  世界已大有变化
And since then, much has changed.
我们将用全新的方式展示
We can now show life on our planet
地球上的生命
in entirely new ways,
带你以前所未有的近距离接触动物
bring you closer to animals than ever before,
首次揭示野生动物的精彩瞬间
and reveal new wildlife dramas for the very first time.
而且不只这些
But that's not all.
我们的星球也在变化
The planet has changed, too.
大自然从未像现在一样
Never have those wildernesses been as fragile
脆弱而又珍贵
and as precious as they are today.
恰逢自然世界这一关键时刻
At this crucial time for the natural world,
我们将再次启航  踏遍全球
we will journey to every corner of the globe
去探索这颗星球上最宝贵的财富
..to explore the greatest treasures of our living planet
去揭秘动物们为了生存  突破的种种极限
and reveal the extreme lengths animals go to to survive.
最后  我们还将回到城市
Finally, we will explore our cities
探寻生命是如何适应这个地球上最新兴的栖息地
to see how life is adapting to the newest habitat on Earth.
这里是《地球脉动》第二季
This is Planet Earth II.
地         球         脉         动   I I
岛        屿
地球上有成千上万的岛屿
There are hundreds of thousands of islands,
每一座岛屿都是一个迷你世界
each one a world in miniature,
是地球的一个缩影
a microcosm of our living planet..
这些偏僻岛屿上为生存所做的努力
The struggles to survive on these remote lands
正如地球上所有生命都要面临的挑战
reflect the challenges faced by all life on Earth.
画 外 音
大卫 · 爱登堡   爵士
巴拿马海岸线边的埃斯库多岛
The tiny island of Escudo off the coast of Panama.
是侏三趾树懒的栖息地
Home to the pygmy three-toed sloth.
这是一只雄性树懒  在这里生活得十分惬意
This is a male, and life here suits him well.
红树林为他提供食物
Mangroves provide all the leaves he can eat
也没有天敌前来叨扰
and there are no predators to worry him.
岛上的生活似牧歌般悠闲
Island life may seem idyllic
但这是有代价的
but it comes at a price.
这座岛上只有几百只雌性侏三指树懒
There are only a few hundred pygmy sloths in existence.
而他需要配偶
And he needs a mate.
这雌性的叫声
That's an enticing call...
好生诱人
..from a female.
就在不远的某个地方
Somewhere out there.
对树懒来说  这反应堪称迅猛
And this, for a sloth, is a quick reaction.
但问题是  中间隔着一渊深潭
The problem is, there's deep water between them.
那么一只气血方刚的树懒会怎么做呢
So what should any red-blooded sloth do?
当然是游过去
Swim, of course.
那会是她吗
Could this be her?
他尽全力加快速度
He does his best to put on a turn of speed.
但叫的不是她
But she's not the one.
这只母树懒已经有了一只幼崽
She already has a baby
在幼崽六个月后长大离开之前
and she won't mate again until it leaves her
她不会再次交配
in about six months' time.
即使生活在天堂之岛也会有限制
Even life on a paradise island can have its limitations.
但至少她就在不远处
But at least she can't be far away.
地球上所有的侏三指树懒都生活在
The world's entire population of pygmy sloths is isolated
这片不及纽约中央公园大小的岛屿上
on a speck of land no bigger than New York's Central Park.
岛屿的大小极大地影响着
The size of an island has a huge influence
生活在那里的动物
on the fate of those cast away there.
这是印度尼西亚的科莫多岛
The island of Komodo in Indonesia.
龙之巢穴
Home to dragons.
体长三米  重达六十八公斤
Ten feet long and weighing an impressive 150 lbs,
他们是地球上现存体型最大的蜥蜴
these are the largest living lizards on the planet.
大型食肉动物在岛屿上并不常见
It's unusual to find large predators on islands.
然而  四百万年来  科莫多巨蜥一直称霸这里
Yet, for four million years, the Komodo dragon has dominated here.
这么小的岛屿似乎不可能
It might seem there wouldn't be enough food
为这种庞然大物提供充足的食物来源
to support such giants on this relatively small island.
但冷血爬行动物只需要
But reptiles, being cold-blooded,
肉食性哺乳动物十分之一的食物量
need only about a tenth of the food a carnivorous mammal would.
巨蜥一餐可以支撑一个月
A single meal will last a dragon a month.
他们的生存之道如此成功  以至于唯一的
They're so successful, that their only serious competition
天敌就是他们的同类
comes from others of their own kind,
而这座岛上有约两千只巨蜥
And there are some 2,000 of them here.
然而这只巨蜥  并不是在寻找食物
This giant however, isn't looking for food.
他在寻找配偶
he's looking for a mate.
雌性巨蜥一年发一次情
Female dragons come into season only once a year.
这一只并不排斥
She's receptive.
目前为止  一切顺利
So far, so good.
但他误入别人的领地
But he's strayed into someone else's patch.
另一只雄性巨蜥认为它才是这里的王
Another huge male thinks he is the king here.
岛屿上空间有限  巨蜥的地盘时常重叠
Space being limited on islands, dragon territories overlap,
导致冲突不断
and that creates continual conflict.
在巨蜥族群里  体型决定一切
In dragon society, size is everything.
但如果双方体型相当  鹿死谁手就难以预料
But if rivals are closely matched, the outcome can be uncertain.
强壮的尾巴一击如同重锤
Muscular tails strike with the power of sledgehammers.
锯齿形状的牙齿像牛排刀一样锋利
And their serrated teeth are as sharp as steak knives.
他们都想要掀翻对手
Each tries to topple his opponent.
胜者出现
Defeated.
只有最强壮的巨蜥  才有权交配
Only the most powerful dragons win the right to mate.
岛屿上有限的食物和空间
The limited food and space on small islands
时常激起激烈的竞争
can often lead to intense competition.
但有些岛屿却幅员辽阔
But some islands are immense.
更像是一块小型大陆
More like miniature continents.
这为不同生命的进化与试验  提供了机会
And these provide opportunities for life to experiment and evolve.
马达加斯加是地球上最大的岛屿之一
Madagascar is one of the biggest islands
也是最古老的岛屿之一
and also one of the oldest,
它在一亿两千万年前就已经脱离非洲大陆
having split away from Africa over 120 million years ago.
随着时间流逝与地理隔断的出现 岛上的动物们不断适应
With time and isolation, its animals have adapted
充分利用一切可用资源
to take advantage of every available niche.
这座岛上现存约二十五万不同的物种
The island now has some 250,000 different species,
大部分都是该地区特有种
most found nowhere else on Earth.
这些不是猴子  而是狐猴
These are not monkeys, but lemurs.
他们从同一个祖先  进化出一百个不同的种
From a single ancestor, about a hundred different types have evolved.
体型最大的马达加斯加大狐猴极少下树
The largest, the indri, seldom comes down from the branches.
体型小许多的环尾狐猴  成群结队地扫荡森林地面
The much smaller ring-tails wander in troops across the forest floor
寻找水果
searching for fruit.
极小的驯狐猴只吃竹子
And tiny bamboo lemurs eat nothing except bamboo.
因为竞争者极少
With few competitors,
狐猴能够在整片岛屿上生活
lemurs have been free to colonise almost every environment on the island,
甚至是环境极其恶劣的地方
Even the most extreme.
这只幼小的冕狐猴成长之路十分艰辛
This baby sifaka has a hard life ahead of it.
他出生在马达加斯加广阔土地上
He's been born in the most arid and hostile corner
最贫瘠干旱的地方
of Madagascar's vast landscape.
他还需要学习很多东西  才能在这存活下去
If he is to survive here, he has much to learn.
刺森林的环境类似沙漠
The spiny forest is like a desert.
由于很少下雨  水和食物都很难获取
It rarely rains, so water and food is very hard to find.
在树间跳跃穿梭十分危险
Moving from tree to tree is a perilous business.
这里几乎所有的植物表面都布满尖刺
Here, nearly all the plants are covered with ferocious spines.
幼崽的妈妈在树顶寻找鲜嫩的叶子
His mother searches the tree tops for the youngest leaves.
嫩叶提供了这个家庭唯一的食物和水
They provide the only food and water to sustain the family.
小狐猴三个月大时便开始探索世界
At three months old, the youngster is starting to explore.
很快他将不得不自己上树寻找食物了
All too soon he will have to fend for himself up here.
但总归还是待在妈妈的背上最轻松
But it's altogether easier to stay on mother's back.
如果他能掌握这片森林中特有的生存方法
If he can master the strange ways of this forest
就能在马达加斯加岛上谋得一席之地
he will have a little corner of Madagascar to himself.
岛屿生态迫使动物另辟蹊径
Island life encourages animals to do things differently.
在某些岛上  这是必备的生存技能
And on some islands that is essential.
由于火山运动
There are islands still forming today
现在仍有岛屿不断形成
built by volcanoes.
有些火山喷发剧烈
Some erupt explosively.
有些则熔化岩石
Others pour out rivers of molten rock.
化作岩浆
Lava.
在近五十年内
In the last 50 years,
已经形成了十个新的火山岛
ten new volcanic islands have been formed.
由于形成时间晚又常十分偏远  鲜有生命踏足
Newly created and often remote, they're hard for colonists to reach.
即使有  环境也极其难以生存
Even those that do find these are tough places to survive.
这是费尔南迪纳岛
This is Fernandina,
太平洋加拉帕戈斯群岛的一部分
one of the Galapagos Islands in the Pacific.
这座年轻的活火山岛屿一片荒凉
Young and still volcanically active, it's a desolate place.
然而环岛的海中却孕育着丰富的生命
The surrounding sea, however, is particularly rich with life.
而这两个不同世界的交界处
And the frontier between these two very different worlds
生活着最奇异的爬行动物
is the home of one of the strangest of reptiles.
海鬣蜥
Seagoing iguanas.
它们是素食者
They are vegetarians,
但由于岛上没有能吃的食物
but since there's little food for them on the land,
所以海鬣蜥以海底的植物为食
marine iguanas graze on the sea floor.
这种体型的雄性海鬣蜥可潜到水下三十米
A big male like this one can dive to 30 metres
屏住呼吸长达半小时
and hold his breath for half an hour.
仅在费尔南迪纳岛上  就有超过七千只海鬣蜥
There are more than 7,000 individuals on Fernandina alone.
它们往返近海获取食物养活自己
And by bringing nutrients from the sea to the land,
同时还帮助了其它动物在此生存
the iguanas help other animals to survive here, too.
红石蟹以海鬣蜥背上的死皮为食
Crabs feed on dead skin on the iguana's back
反过来也热情地为它们提供去角质服务
and, in turn, provide a welcome exfoliation service.
小型蜥蜴还捕食纠缠海鬣蜥的苍蝇
While smaller lizards prey on the flies that pester the colony.
但岛上的生存关系并不是都如此和谐
But not all the relationships on this island are so harmonious.
海鬣蜥将蛋下在沙子里
Marine iguanas lay their eggs in sand.
每到六月  刚破壳的小鬣蜥异常脆弱
In June, when the hatchlings emerge, they are vulnerable.
它们必须到海边与成年海鬣蜥汇合
They must join the adults at the edge of the sea.
但这将是一次危险的旅程
But the journey will be a dangerous one.
游蛇
Racer snakes.
游蛇错失了这次机会
The snakes miss their chance.
但还有更多的小鬣蜥将孵化而出
But more babies are hatching.
这些游蛇正虎视眈眈
And now the snakes are on the alert.
这是它们一年里最佳的捕食时机
This is the best feeding opportunity they will get all year.
小鬣蜥在平地上跑得比游蛇快
On flat ground, a baby iguana can outrun a racer snake.
但周围还有其他蛇在埋伏
But others are waiting in ambush.
另一只刚孵化的小鬣蜥  第一次见识了这个危险的世界
Another hatchling has its first glimpse of a dangerous world.
蛇的视力并不是很好  但它们可以感知到移动物体
A snake's eyes aren't very good, but they can detect movement.
所以如果这只小鬣蜥能保持冷静 也许能逃出它们的视线
So if the hatch ling keeps its nerve, it may just avoid detection.
近乎奇迹地逃出生天
A near miraculous escape.
有幸活下来的小鬣蜥可以开始学习
The lucky survivors can begin learning the unique way of life
应对这座危险岛屿的独特方式了
demanded by this hostile island.
尽管海鬣蜥是游泳的行家
Although marine iguanas are expert swimmers,
它们也无法横渡广阔的大海
they can't cross open oceans.
但再汹涌的海水都无法阻挡鸟类
But even the stormiest waters are no barrier for birds.
阵阵烈风加之低温
Gale force winds and cold temperatures
让新西兰亚南极地区的这座岛屿
make the subantarctic islands off New Zealand
在冬天变得尤其不友好
particularly unwelcoming in winter.
但当短暂的夏日来临时  这里将变得风和日丽
But when the brief summer comes, temperatures rise and winds slacken.
正是游客到访的好时节
It's now that visitors arrive.
都趁着冬天来临之前来这里繁殖
All here to breed before winter returns.
这些是斯岛黄眉企鹅
There's the Snares penguins.
海鸥也来到这里
Shearwaters come, too.
因为没有天敌能够靠近这里
This is an excellent place for them to dig their nesting burrows,
这里成为海鸥挖掘地窝的绝佳场所
for no predators have managed to get here.
很快岛上会到处都是鸟
Soon the island is crowded with birds.
每只鸟都急切地想充分利用  他们短暂的繁育季节
Every one of them eager to make the most of the short breeding season.
但并不是所有鸟都有伴侣
But not everyone has a partner.
一只雄性新西兰信天翁正等待另一半的到来
A male Buller's albatross waits for his mate.
每年他们都将分开六个月  各自在海上飞行
Each year they spend six months apart, travelling the ocean.
他们将在这里汇合生育下一代
They reunite here to breed.
但今年  雌性信天翁还没有到
But this year, she's late.
不  那不是她
No, that's not her.
其他鸟儿来来往往
The other birds come and go.
时间所剩无几
The clock is ticking.
如果雌性信天翁还不出现 他们将错过顺利繁衍后代的机会
If she doesn't appear soon, it will be too late for them to breed successfully.
每天清晨海鸥飞离这里  为他们的孩子寻找食物
Every morning the shearwaters fly off to collect food for their young.
每只鸟儿似乎都在抓紧干
Everybody else seems to be getting on with it.
海鸥的归来意味着又一天过去了
The shearwaters' return marks another lost day.
这个岛上有三百万只鸟
There are three million birds on the island,
但他只在乎那一只
but only one matters to him.
这会是她吗
Could this be her?
总算回来啦
At last.
一开始雄性信天翁还有些害羞
At first, he's a little coy.
但很快就放开了
But not for long.
他们用多年来练成的独特舞蹈
They greet each other with the special dance
向彼此表示问候
they've perfected over many years.
如果他们还打算在冬天来临前养育孩子 要做的事情还有很多
There is much to do, if they're to raise a chick before winter returns.
但当你和某人分开大半年
But when you have been apart for six months,
有些事需要慢慢来
some things can't be rushed.
地处温暖热带海域的岛屿  无法体验极端的季节变化
Islands in warm tropical waters don't experience seasonal extremes.
位于非洲东海岸的塞舌尔群岛
The Seychelles, lying off the coast of East Africa,
是海鸟们全年的庇护天堂
provide a sanctuary for sea birds all the year round.
塞舌尔白燕鸥是这里的永久居民
Fairy Terns are permanent residents.
它们筑巢并不讲究
They take a fairly relaxed view about what constitutes a nest.
一根光秃秃的树枝就足够了
A bare branch is quite enough.
不过爬上去孵蛋需要格外小心
Climbing onto it to incubate has to be done with care.
每年白燕鸥都会来一次
Once a year, the noddies arrive.
它们老实筑窝  腺果藤树能让
They do make nests, and Pisonia trees
小鸟的幼年过得安全一些
provide their young with a rather less precarious start in life.
在这个岛上筑巢看起来几乎完美
Nesting on this island looks idyllic.
但美丽的表象后也有危险的一面
But behind the beauty, there's a sinister side.
塞舌尔福迪雀偷袭了无人照看的蛋
The Seychelles fody makes quick work of an unattended egg.
她知道事情有点不太对劲
She knows something's not quite right,
但她孵化的意愿很强烈
but her drive to incubate is strong.
黑燕鸥也遇上了麻烦
The noddies too have a problem.
随着雏鸟一天天长大
As their chicks grow,
腺果藤树长出了黏黏的
so the pisonia trees develop seeds that are sticky
带有倒钩的种子
and equipped with hooks.
新一代黑燕鸥离巢的时候
By the time the young noddies leave,
会带着这些搭顺风车的种子前往其它岛屿
they carry these hitchhiking seeds away to other islands.
但有时腺果藤树的策略过于成功
But sometimes the pisonia trees are too successful.
如果幼鸟在学习飞翔时跌落地面
If a fledgling, testing out its wings, drops to the ground,
它身上会挂满这些种子
it can get covered with the seeds.
汁液粘腻  越粘越重
Entangled and weighed down,
如果它摆脱不了  就会饿死
if it can't free itself,the youngster will starve.
这样腺果藤的种子无法传播
The Pisonia may have failed to disperse these seeds,
但种子扎根很快就有好肥料了
but it will soon have fertiliser for its roots.
这也是人们称腺果藤树为“捕鸟树”的原因
This is why some people call the pisonia the "Bird catcher tree".
白燕鸥又下了一颗蛋
The fairy tern laid another egg,
现在她要养一只小鸟了
and now she has a tiny chick to feed.
这只小鸟很幸运
This chick is lucky.
等它羽翼丰满之时  腺果藤树种子已经传播完毕
By the time it fledges, the Pisonia seeds will have dispersed
它们带来的危险也将不复存在
and the danger they brought will be gone.
再诗情画意的岛屿
Even the most idyllic looking of islands
岛上的动物也要面临挑战
presents challenges for the animals living there.
但它们眼前的最大威胁已经改变
But the greatest threat they face is change.
这是印度洋上的圣诞岛
Christmas Island in the Indian Ocean.
数百万年以来  这块遥远的陆地一直被蟹类统治着
For millions of years this remote spec of land has been ruled by crabs.
它们的祖先来自海洋
Their ancestors came from the sea,
但绝大多数品种现在已经适应了陆地上的生活
but most have now adopted a land-based existence.
鉴于它们的数量众多  彼此之间还算相对和谐
Given there are so many of them, they get along relatively harmoniously.
它们是这个小小蟹类乌托邦的园丁和守卫
They're the gardeners and caretakers of a tiny crab utopia.
每年它们都会回到海洋中进行繁殖
Once a year, they must all return to the sea to breed,
而红蟹大迁徙
and the march of the red crabs
是地球是最伟大的自然奇观之一
is one of the greatest natural spectacles on earth.
迁徙的红蟹数量多达五千万只
There are 50 million of them.
这一景象让这座岛屿举世闻名
It's an event that has brought the island worldwide fame.
但近些年来
But in recent years,
数以百万的红蟹未能成功抵达海洋
millions of red crabs haven't managed to reach the sea.
一种入侵物种占领了这座岛屿
An invader has occupied this island.
黄疯蚁
Yellow crazy ants.
它们搭乘来访的船只来到岛上  由于缺乏天敌控制
They escape from visiting ships, and with no predators
它们在森林里建立了
to control them, they have now created vast
巨大的超级蚁群
super colonies in the forest.
当迁徙的红蟹经过它们的领地时
When migrating red crabs march into their territory,
黄疯蚁便展开攻击
the ants attack.
它们朝红蟹的双眼和嘴中喷射酸液
Squirting acid into the crabs' eyes and mouths.
红蟹毫无还手之力
The crabs have no defence.
双目失明  迷失方向  它们便死定了
Blinded and confused, they're doomed.
是人类把这些蚂蚁入侵者带上了岛
Humans brought these ant invaders here,
而现在人类不得不采取措施控制局面
and now humans are having to control them.
与世隔绝的动物群落 可能在数百万年内演化出了相对稳定的生态
Isolated communities may evolve for millions of years in relative peace,
但当新挑战来袭  它们只能尽力去应对
But, when new challenges arrive, they can struggle to cope.
近年来濒于灭绝的物种之中
Of all the species that have become extinct in recent years,
大约百分之八十是岛屿物种
around 80% have been islanders.
人类对地球所造成的影响  比以往任何时候都要深远
Our impact on the Earth is greater today than ever before.
然而有些岛屿是如此偏远
Yet some islands are so remote
以至于几乎没有人类踏足
that few humans have even set foot on them.
扎沃多夫斯基岛就是一例
Zavodovski Island is one.
它地处南太平洋
It lies in the great Southern Ocean.
不仅被最猛烈的海洋风暴所环绕
It's not only surrounded by the stormiest of seas,
而且本身就是座活火山
it is itself an active volcano.
这里是地球上你最不愿居住的地方
It's the last place on Earth you would choose to live.
除非你是一只南极帽带企鹅
Unless you're a chinstrap penguin.
这里的水域食物充足  但若想享用美食
There is plenty of food in these waters, but to exploit it,
这些企鹅得冒着生命危险
the penguins have to risk their lives.
这里的生活险象环生
Life here is dangerous in the extreme.
但生活在火山上还是有一些好处的
But there are some benefits from living on a volcano.
火山的热量每年早早地融化了积雪
Its warmth melts the snow early in the year.
到了一月  南极地区的仲夏时节
And, by January, the Antarctic's mid-summer,
整座岛被小企鹅覆盖
the island is covered in chicks.
双亲轮流守护幼崽
Parents take turns at guarding them
直到它们成长到足以独立生活
until they're large enough to be left alone.
这几只小鸟饿了  但母亲没有食物可以喂它们
This mother's chicks are hungry, but she has no food left to give them.
生存与否取决于它们的父亲  能否带着食物归来
Their survival depends on their father returning with their next meal.
有些企鹅确实一去不返
But some don't make it.
贼鸥不断侵扰着企鹅种群  希望能趁机叼走一只雏鸟
Skuas harass the colony hoping to snatch a chick.
母亲不能冒险离开自己的雏鸟
She can't risk leaving them.
只要父亲尽快回来  情况就会好转
Everything will be fine, as long as their father comes back soon.
他前往远离海岸八十公里的海域捕鱼
He's been fishing 50 miles offshore,
但他现在离家不远了
but now he's not far away.
对于他和这里所有的企鹅父母来说
For him, however, and for all the other parents here,
归途中最糟糕的一段还在后面
the worst of the journey is still to come.
他的小脚爪帮助他攀附住陡峭的火山岩
Tiny claws help him to get whatever grip he can on the rough lava.
对于这些往返的企鹅来说  现在是高峰时刻
For these commuters, it's rush hour.
有些企鹅今天不太顺利
Some have had a really bad day.
这位父亲要走三公里的路才能到家
The father now has a two-mile walk to the nest,
肚里塞满食物  路越发难走
and a stomach loaded with food doesn't help.
周围还有全球数量最庞大的企鹅种群
This is the largest penguin colony in the world.
但由于他每隔一天就要走一遍
But as he makes the same journey every other day,
闭着眼睛都能找到回巢的路
he should be able to do it with his eyes closed.
巨大的种群数量确实能保证安全
It's true that there can be safety in numbers,,
但当你试图寻找自己的巢穴之时
but numbers can also be something of a problem
这也会成为问题
when you're trying to find your own nest.
母亲依然在等待
The mother is still waiting.
小鸟们快要绝望了
Her chicks are now desperate.
在这震耳欲聋的叫声之中
In the midst of all this deafening chorus,
他可以辨识出对方特有的声音
he can recognise her particular cry.
总算回来了
At last.
两只雏鸟都能饱餐一顿
Both chicks will get a meal.
点头示意之后  他们的母亲出发了
With a head bob of acknowledgement, their mother now leaves.
轮到她外出捕食了
It's her turn to do the feeding run.
这种艰难的往返  是这些企鹅为了庇护所付出的代价
This formidable commute is the price these penguins pay for sanctuary.
也许在我们看来  这样的天堂很奇怪
A strange vision of paradise to us, perhaps,
但是对于一百五十万只企鹅来说
but, for one and a half million penguins,
这座岛屿满足了全部所需
this island has it all.
岛屿可能既偏远而又微不足道
Islands may seem remote and insignificant,
但它们仍是地球上某些珍贵动物的家园
but they are home to some of the most precious wildlife on Earth.
下一集
Next time,
我们会到地球的高山
we ascend into the planet's high mountains
发现一个壮观但充满敌意的世界
to discover a spectacular but hostile word.
生活在那儿必须足智多谋
where life must be at its most resourceful,
只有生命力最顽强的动物可以忍受
and only the toughest animals can endure.